Student Activities Office: Subject Folders UA292 UA292
University of Rochester
Student Activities Office: Subject Folders
1926-1968, bulk 1955-1967
University of Rochester Rush Rhees Library 500 Joseph C. Wilson Blvd Rochester, New York 14627 rchives@library.rochester.edu http://www.library.rochester.edu
UA292
12.25 Linear Feet 25 boxes, 1 flat file
Restrictions on Access
For access to this collection, please contact the University of Rochester Archives (archives@library.rochester.edu) at least two business days prior to your planned visit.
Please note: Some materials may be restricted or require permission for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Received from Marc Hoberman (Class of 1970), October 1968.
Arrangement
Oversize materials have been shifted to flat file.
Biographical / Historical
The College of Arts and Science Bulletin for 1931-1932 described "extra-curricular activities... as a means of promoting the education and developing the character of all students." While pointing to their potential value in "the development of a rounded individual," the University noted that student activities should not be compulsory because they depend on students' interest, available time, and academic work (page 45).
This collection bridges the period when the University was coordinate—with a separate College for men and College for Women—and after it became coeducational in 1955. Student activities for men were housed in Todd Union, one of the original buildings on the River Campus that opened in 1930. During the period from 1930 to 1955, the College for Women continued to remain on the Prince Street Campus, where their Student Activities Office was located in Cutler Union. When the Colleges for Men and Women integrated in 1955 on the River Campus, their activities offices consolidated as well. Todd Union was redesigned at this time to suit its new coeducational role. Several offices, such as the Dietary Office, were moved out of the building to accommodate the larger student body that would use the space. Kitchen facilities were also downsized in Todd Union as two new dining halls were added on the River Campus, and this created more room for activities.
Cornelis de Kiewiet was the president of the University at the time of the merger, having been inaugurated in 1951. The 1955-1956 issue of the College of Arts and Science Bulletin noted that, "Under [his] leadership there has been a sharpening of educational purpose at Rochester based on the conviction that 'we must concentrate on the coordination and efficiency of all those activities which constitute each student's total educational experience'" (page 18). Therefore, in 1955 Todd Union became a center of student activities for all students. Residence Hall governments provided activities as well, but these were often limited to the residents of those buildings and were not coeducational for the most part. At Todd Union, men's and women's groups often merged into a single entity; for example, The Campus newspaper from the men's college and The Tower Times newspaper from the women's college merged into the Campus Times.
The Student Activities Office in Todd Union for most of the first 35 years was staffed by a director, assistant director, and secretary. As the student body at the University grew more rapidly in the 1960s, the office expanded to include other staff as well. Several members of the office staff figure prominently in the collection: Jane Stellwagen (Class of 1947), Assistant Dean of Students from 1961-1965 and Director of Student Activities from 1958-1962; Martin Van de Visse, Director of Student Activities from 1962-1964, Director of Student Life in 1963, and Assistant to the Dean of Students in 1964; Marion "Rusty" Dearnley (Class of 1960), Assistant Director of Student Activities from 1962-1963, Associate Director of Student Life from 1963-1964, and Director of Student Activities from 1964-1965; and Vicki Proschel Schwartz (Class of 1962), Director of Student Activities from 1965-1967. Other University administrators whose names frequently appear in the collection are Alice Corbin, Director of Residence Halls for Women from 1960-1963 and Director of Residence Halls from 1963-1965; Alexander Cameron, Associate Dean of Students from 1961-1963 and Dean of Students 1963-1965; and Joseph Cole, Assistant Dean of Students from 1956-1959, Dean of Students from 1959-1963, University Dean of Student Affairs from 1963-1967, and Associate Provost of Student Life from 1967-1968.
Related Materials
Additional material can be found in the Student Activities Office: Subject Folders, 1933-1964, collection.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of subject folders maintained by the Student Activities Office at Todd Union. The material dates from 1926 to 1968. Several items date from before the opening of Todd Union, and bulk dates for the material are 1955-1967. For the period before integration of the women's and men's colleges (1930-1955), material is only for the College for Men. The collection covers a range of topics, including student government, fraternities and sororities, Freshman orientation ("Frosh Week"), student organizations, administrative groups, and material about the Student Activities Office and Todd Union themselves. These folders were the office's records on clubs and other activities, and the material in the folders primarily reflects what the groups themselves collected. Materials include correspondence, University press releases, notes, budgets, constitutions, meeting minutes, newsletters, reports, and membership lists.
Dates refer to when materials were created. Files related to Frosh Week and Parents Weekend also contain, as an integral part of the title, dates that refer to when those events were held.
Bibliography
Bulletin of the University of Rochester: College of Arts and Science Catalogue, 1931-1932. University of Rochester, 1930.
Bulletin of the University of Rochester: College of Arts and Science, Issue for 1955-1956. University of Rochester, 1955.
Cameron, Alexander. Public Relations Faculty/Staff Files, Series 2, Dept. of Rare Books, Special Collections, and Preservation, University of Rochester.
Cole, Joseph. Public Relations Faculty/Staff Files, Series 2, Dept. of Rare Books, Special Collections, and Preservation, University of Rochester.
Corbin, Alice. Public Relations Faculty/Staff Files, Series 2, Dept. of Rare Books, Special Collections, and Preservation, University of Rochester.
Dearnley, Marion. Public Relations Faculty/Staff Files, Series 2, Dept. of Rare Books, Special Collections, and Preservation, University of Rochester.
Pieterse, Janice Bullard. Our Work Is But Begun. Meliora Press, 2014.
Schwartz, Vicki. Public Relations Faculty/Staff Files, Series 1, Dept. of Rare Books, Special Collections, and Preservation, University of Rochester.
Stellwagen, Jane. Public Relations Faculty/Staff Files, Series 2, Dept. of Rare Books, Special Collections, and Preservation, University of Rochester.
Van de Visse, Martin. Public Relations Faculty/Staff Files, Series 1, Dept. of Rare Books, Special Collections, and Preservation, University of Rochester.
- Academic Reports, Performance Programs, 1959-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes material on academic advising, admitted students (to and about them), and academic honesty.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Second folder contains confidential information.
- Activities Program, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes material on Student Activities advisors and draft card policies at the University.
- All-University Symphony Orchestra, 1956-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Includes several concert programs.
- Alpha Phi Omega, 1957-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  Includes material on the Ugliest Man on Campus (UMOC) charity event, event posters, and forms for advertising space on University desk blotters (the desk pad that was sold to University students and had the school calendar on it).
- Alumni Office, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Amateur Radio Club, 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes correspondence about the club's establishment.
- Americans for Reappraisal of Far Eastern Policy, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes a document inviting professors to the first meeting.
- Arts Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes a student activities calendar, conference brochure for an English conference at the University, and creative arts festival booklet from the student union at the University of Michigan.
- Arts Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes event listings and event proposals.
- Arts Committee, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes events calendars, correspondence with the Danish, Swedish, and Norwegian embassies about a Scandinavian Arts Festival to be held in 1961 in Rochester, a poster for the Scandinavian Arts Festival, and correspondence between United States senate offices and the Soviet Union embassy about a 1960 Russian Arts Festival.
- Arts Committee, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Includes brochures for performance groups and contracts with groups.
- Arts Committee, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes pamphlets for the 1960 Russian Arts Festival and the 1961 Scandinavian Arts Festival, annotated concert programs, and an unidentified photograph.
  Separated Materials
  Photocopies of photographs are available in this folder. Originals were moved to the University Photographs collection in a folder with the same name.
- Arts Committee, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes many programs for performances by University groups and outside groups.
- Association for the International Education of Students in Economics and Commerce, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Contains an open letter inviting students to attend an information session and a press release about summer internships.
- Association of Women Students, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Includes planning documents, forms, and assessment reports for the 1964 region IV convention of the International Association of Women Students (IAWS) held at the University of Rochester.
- Association of Women Students: Budgets, 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Includes information about a conference at Massachusetts Institute of Technology for women in science.
- Association of Women Students: Bulletins and Minutes, 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  Includes AWS Council, Executive Council, and Dorm Council minutes.
- Association of Women Students: Elections, Programs, Constitutions, Correspondence, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  Includes officer lists, election ballots, event posters, a report from the National Association of Women Deans and Councilors, and correspondence from other colleges asking for documents from the University.
- Association of Women Students: General File, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes a nomination form for the "Best-Dressed Girl on Campus" competition, a flyer for a sex information seminar, and a handmade invitation to a Pajama Party addressed to Rusty Dearnley.
- Association of Women Students: Handbook, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Contains the 1964/1965 handbook, drafts of the handbook and other planning material, and the Towers Residents' Handbook for 1965/1966.
- Association of Women Students: Hours, Curfews, Standards Committee, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Contains a document titled "History of the Curfew System 1955-1964," evaluation reports on the curfews, and petition forms for late hours.
- Association of Women Students: Women's Residence Hall Council, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Contains a mailing envelope that held material for a booklet on residence hall life including seven photographs.
- Bands, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Contains a letter about improper cleanup of the snack bar in Todd Union and a memo about bands using rooms in Todd Union for rehearsals.
- Baroque Ensemble, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Contains three concert programs, one with notes on it.
- Bellman's Society, 1952-1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Includes performance announcements.
- Board of Control, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Contains the constitution and bylaws in document and booklet form.
- Board of Control: Statements, Balance Sheets, Budgets, 1945-1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Bowling, 1959-1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Includes correspondence with Hobart College about seasonal matches, budgets, and tournament posters.
- Bridge Club, 1959-1965 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Includes club posters and posters about the University of Rochester International Bridge Competition.
- Budgets, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Contains budgets for the College Cabinet, Campus Times, and the Print Shop.
- Budgets, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Contains budgets for the International Relations Club, Red Cross, Arts Committee, Women's Recreation Association, and Student Activities Office. Also included are memos about keys to Todd Union.
- Budgets, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Contains Interfraternity Council budgets and a publication for fraternities titled "Key to House Financing: 'Fiscal Responsibility.'"
- Buildings and Space, 1952-1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Includes a memo about the naming of buildings in the Founders Court and Graduate Living Center, a memo about summer programs for children of faculty, schedules for lights in Rush Rhees Library's tower, and a memo on the expansion of the Atomic Energy Project at the medical school.
- Calendars and Directories, 1956-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  Directories are of Student Activities groups. Also includes city calendars and workshop schedules.
- Campus Conference on Religion, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Includes programs, posters, and questionnaires.
- Campus Security and Parking, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Also includes bus schedule, building openings, and "Late Hours" requests.
- Campus Times, 1948-1967 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  Includes publishing schedules, subscription forms, advertising requests, a style guide for reporting the news, fundraising and reports about sending a reporter to Southern University to investigate that school's closing due to protests against segregation, subscribers list, and postage calculation forms.
- Chaperone Checklist Forms, 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Also includes letters requesting chaperones for functions and "Instructions and Information for the Night Managers."
- Chaperone Lists, 1956-1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Also includes a letter to student organizations on what their chaperone requests should look like.
- Chess Club, 1952-1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Includes event posters, result booklets from tournaments, and correspondence with several colleges during a period when the University did not have an active club.
- Chronicle, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Includes a letter from Ward Woodbury (Orchestral Conductor and Director) about missing concerts in the calendar and a draft, with notes, for the 1965/1966 school year edition.
  Biographical / Historical
  This publication was established in 1959. As indicated on the front cover it includes "a listing of officers and advisors of the major student organizations and the publishing of a daily calendar with major university events listed."
- City Students, 1956-1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Lists of commuter students (City Students), reports on beds on campus that were reserved for commuter students if they decided to sleep on campus for the night, material from the City Women's Organization, a letter on the Books for Asian Students project, and programs for father-daughter banquets.
  Books for Asian Students was a nonprofit organization that provided textbooks in English to universities in Asian countries.
- Co-Kast, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Many performance programs, posters, and room reservation requests.
  Co-Kast was a musical theater group that focused on comedy. Its first play was George Gershwin's Girl Crazy in the fall of 1958.
- College Bowl, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Contains a booklet for the 1965/1966 season.
- Commencement and Baccalaureate, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Includes schedules, programs, and reports on commencement.
- Commencement: Marshals, Ushers, and Other Arrangements, 1957-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Also includes reviews of the ceremonies by the Commencement Committee and Student Activities Office.
- Composite Photographs, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Concert Band, 1957-1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Contains concert programs, information about the name change to "Symphonic Band" in 1966, and a marching band attendance policy.
- Concessions Committee, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Includes lists of concessions, a charter for the committee, documents (financial, constitutions) from Rochester Contrast, and an advertisement for Towers Laundry.
  This committee was composed of deans and staff members. It gave permits to and oversaw student vendors on campus for various products such as Avon, Playboy, and charter buses.
- Conference Office, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Contains a report on activities from July 1, 1965 through June 30, 1966.
- Contrast, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Includes subscription forms, posters, surveys on the military draft, a WRUR Fan-Gram poster on basketball, and four issues from 1965 with annotations.
  Rochester Contrast was first published in fall 1964 as an alternative campus paper to the Campus Times and other publications. It strove to fill the need for "more information and communication presented on a basis differently from that of any presently existing or proposed method on campus." It was originally a concession granted by the Concession Committee, but became a student activity under the Student Activities Office in 1965.
- Dandelion Day, 1963-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Contains programs for the event and an issue of the Campus Times from April 30, 1968.
- Dean's Office Staff, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Includes material pertaining to events for Dean's Office staff, such as parties and picnics.
  A guidebook for parents of freshman students from 1963 has been moved to the Orientatin collection.
- Dean's Reports, 1956-1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Includes withdrawals lists; enrollment data; summer job opportunities for juniors; academic and annual reports; and a list of pre-medical and pre-dental students, their grades, and which graduate schools they were accepted into.
  Contains confidential information.
- Displays and Bulletin Boards, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- D'Lions, 1958-1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Contains programs for dinners put on by the group, babysitting posters, applications, acceptance letters, rejection letter forms, evaluation forms, meeting agendas, and schedules for tour guides.
  At the time of the material the D'Lions were the women's sophomore honor society.
- Dormitories: Interhall Council, Dorm Constitutions, 1960-1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Includes the Social Behavior Board coed hours policy, party posters, help wanted posters, Open House Committee annual report, and resident adviser application materials.
- Dramatics, 1961-1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  Includes schedules of activities, the draft of a Campus Times article, and an Esso World Theatre program booklet.
- Drug Education Program, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Contains program packets: the program's event calendar, educational booklets on drugs, research papers on drugs and their effects in society, lecture transcripts, and a chart of the most common drugs and their effects and other statistics.
- Eastman School of Music, 1958-1965 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  Includes documents about the organization of Eastman School performances on the River Campus, an interview with Howard Hanson (the Director of the Eastman School of Music), and programs, posters, and season schedules.
- Employee Benefits, 1960-1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  Includes a University career brochure, airplane ticket forms, physician time schedules, insurance coverage for carpools and travel insurance, sick leave policy, and information on tuition benefits for staff.
- Equipment: Correspondence, Contracts, Service Information, 1957-1966 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Evaluations, 1958-1962 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  Contains an evaluation of extracurricular activities at the University. It has a response to the Middle States Report as well as a report from a group from other universities that was brought in to evaluate the University.
- Experiment '60, 1956-1966 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  Includes tryout posters, programs, playbills, and event posters. Also includes material from the Players in the 1950s.
  The group was founded in 1956 under the name of the Players,\ but became Experiment '60 in the 1959/1960 school year. Its name then changed each academic year to the next numeral. For example, in the 1962/1963 academic year, the name changed to Experiment '63. The organization was founded to allow students to be involved "in all aspects of theater" and "to gain experience with plays of their own choice." There was also an emphasis on "creativity and originality" in this company.
- Faculty, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  Includes appointments of staff, information on faculty advisors, and a directory of department officials.
- Faculty Club, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  Contains menus, calendars, club polices and house rules.
- Fencing Club, probably 1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Contains a single poster advertising a meeting.
- Flag Rush, 1957-1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Contains material on both the men's and women's traditions. Includes evaluation reports from the event chairman.
- Forbes Society, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Contains a single document about the group's reformation and first event.
  This was a philosophical organization.
- Foreign Students: Orientation, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  Contains a review of how the orientation went that year by the organizing committee co-chairmen.
- Forensic, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Includes registration forms for tournaments and schedules.
  This was a debate organization on campus.
- Fraternities, 1963-1966 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  Includes informal initiation schedules submitted to the Student Activities Office, a document titled "University Expectations and Assistance for Fraternities," lists of chapters on campus and of freshmen on campus, national chapter rankings, and a booklet for freshmen or other prospective fraternity members about Greek life at the University.
- Fraternities: Alpha Delta Phi, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  Includes a pledge exam.
- Fraternities: Alpha Epsilon Pi, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Fraternities: Alpha Kappa Phi, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Fraternities: Beta Delta Gamma, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  Includes pledge questionnaires.
- Fraternities: Chi Phi, 1961-1965 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  Includes schedules of events and a chapter history.
  The fraternity chapter was originally a local fraternity called Gamma Sigma Phi, which then affiliated with the national fraternity Chi Phi, and some material is from when the fraternity was still called Gamma Sigma Phi.
- Fraternities: Delta Kappa Epsilon, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Fraternities: Delta Upsilon, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Fraternities: Phi Epsilon Pi, approximately 1964 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Fraternities: Psi Upsilon, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Fraternities: Rushing, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  Contains a questionnaire for students about to enter the rushing process.
- Fraternities: Scholarship, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  Contains the rankings of fraternities based on GPA.
- Fraternities: Sigma Alpha Mu, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  Includes kitchen and dining room rules for their house and information on dues.
- Fraternities: Sigma Chi, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  Includes a poster for an event raising money for the Ugliest Man on Campus contest and information about Derby Day (rules, schedules, brochures).
- Fraternities: Tau Kappa Epsilon, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  Includes a pledge final, Oak Leaves newsletter, and TKE tutor lists.
- Fraternities: Theta Chi, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 22)